A Guide to the John K. Martin Records, 1777-1907
Library of Virginia
- Personal Correspondence, 1826-1907 and n.d., 0.45 cubic feet. (Box 29)
  - John K. Martin, 1847-1907, 0.22 cubic feet. (Box 29)
    Personal correspondence, 1847-1907 and n.d., exchanged between Martin and family members and friends. A small group of letters relates to fraternal organizations of which Martin was a member. There is also correspondence with and concerning the Jennings family and the Richmond, Fredericksburg, and Potomac Railway concerning his disatisfaction with railcar service. Correspondence also exists between John K. Martin and the Wallace family of Richmond, Virginia, and a small portion of correspondence written by and concerning the Wallace family of Richmond, Virginia, postdates Martin's death.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent with individual items within the folder arranged chronologically.
    - Fraternal organizations, 1850-1882 and n.d. (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - General, 1849-1869 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - General, 1870-1879 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - General, 1880-1882 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - General, n.d. (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Love letters, 1867-1870 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Jennings family, 1872-1873 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railway, 1847 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Wallace family, 1875-1907 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Michael Howell, 1826-1877 and n.d., 0.22 cubic feet. (Box 29)
    Personal correspondence, 1826-1877 and n.d., exchanged between Howell and family members and friends. Principally concerns family matters, difficulty with tenants on family properties, and family real estate purchases and sales and recommendations for acquaintances land transactions. Undated envelopes that were previously separated from their respective correspondence are included at the end of this subseries.
    - 1826-1827 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - 1832-1837 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - 1840-1849 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - 1850-1853 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - 1854-1877 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Envelopes (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - Palmeter Family, 1852, 1 folder. (Box 29, Folder 17)
    Personal correspondence, 1852, exchanged between Palmeter family members and concerning family events and family matters.
- Financial Files, 1815-1882 and n.d., 1.32 cubic feet. (Boxes 30-33)
  Financial files, 1815-1882 and n.d., consisting of receipts and accounts for John K. Martin and his sometime business partner John R. Fulford of Richmond, Virginia. Receipts and accounts for John Martin generally note purchases for various and sundry goods, rent payments, the purchase of slave labor, and legal service fees from clerks of court. There are also receipt books for land warrants, extra pay and other money received by Martin and William M. Fulton and account books noting state taxes received and miscellaneous business accounts for Michael Howell. An account book for an unidentified carpenter is also contained in this series.
  Arranged in two subseries: A. Receipts and accounts, B. Account books and volumes.
  - Receipts and accounts, 1844-1882 and n.d., 0.6 cubic feet. (Boxes 30-31)
    Receipts and accounts, 1844-1882 and n.d., of John K. Martin generally noting purchases for various and sundry goods from Richmond area merchants, rent payments made to Richmond landlords, and slave labor. Also includes legal service fees receipts from clerks of court. The bulk of the receipts and accounts are for Martin but there are also receipts for John R. Fulford, a sometimes business partner of Martin.
    Arranged chronologically by year with individual receipts within each folder arranged by month. Clerk of court, slave, and John R. Fulford receipts are filed separate from the other receipts and accounts and are filed at the end of the subseries.
    - Receipts, 1844-1851 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Receipts, 1852 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Receipts, 1853 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1854 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Receipts, 1855 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Receipts, 1856 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Receipts, 1857 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Receipts, 1858-1859 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Receipts, 1860-1882 and n.d. (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Receipts, 1844-1861 and n.d. (Box 34a, Folder 5)
    - Receipts (clerks), 1850-1853 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Receipts (clerks), 1853-1855 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Receipts (clerks), 1855-1857 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Receipts (clerks), 1858-1881 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Receipts (slave), 1851, 1856 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - John R. Fulford receipts, 1847-1857 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - Account books and volumes, 1815-1861 and n.d., 0.72 cubic feet. (Boxes 31-33)
    Account books and volumes, 1815-1861 and n.d., There are also receipt books for land warrants, extra pay, and other money received by Martin and fellow land agent William M. Fulton and account books noting state taxes received and miscellaneous business accounts for Michael Howell. An account book for an unidentified carpenter is also contained in this series as is a ledger of legal fees. There is also a bank book for Elijah Brown for whom Martin was the estate administrator and account books for the Wallace family.
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Elijah Brown bank book, 1846-1849 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Ledger of legal fees, 1849-1851 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Michael Howell account books, 1850-1859 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Michael Howell state taxes received account book, 1854-1855 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Receipt books for land warrants, extra pay and other money received by Martin and William M. Fulton, 1848-1854 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - Receipt books for land warrants, extra pay and other money received by Martin and William M. Fulton, 1855-1861 and n.d. (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Unidentified carpenter's account book, 1815-1817 (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified individual's account book, 1867-1871 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified individual's account book, n.d. (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Wallace family account books, 1869, 1876 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Wallace family account books, 1870-1890 (Box 33, Folder 4)
- Administrator's Files, 1816-1858, 0.23 cubic feet. (Boxes 33)
  Administrator's files, 1816-1858, of John K. Martin, who served as administrator for Elijah Brown (1781-1850). Consists of accounts and receipts, correspondence, legal files, and Bible records proving family line and beneficiaries.
  Arranged alphabetically with individual items within each folder arranged chronologically.
  - Accounts and receipts, 1848-1850 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Accounts and receipts, 1851-1854 (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Brown-Ballow family Bible records, 1841-1850 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1818-1858 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Court records and deeds, 1816-1854 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Court records and deeds, 1846, 1853 (Box 34a, Folder 6)
- Military Files, 1775-1781, 1820-1857 and n.d., 0.23 cubic feet. (Boxes 34)
  Military files, 1775-1781, 1820-1853 and n.d., consisting of discharge papers, 1820-1853 and n.d., including discharge certificates for veterans, a list of Revolutionary War battles, lists of officers and soldiers from various wars, military returns, and military payrolls.
  Arranged in two subseries: A. Discharge Papers, B. Rolls and Lists.
  - Discharge Papers, 1820-1853 and n.d., 0.11 cubic feet. (Box 34)
    Arranged alphabetically by surname with individual items within each folder arranged chronologically.
    - Discharge Papers - Allen-Dunston (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Allen, Jonathan, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Archer, Thomas F. R., 1824 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Bair, Robert, 1828 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Basserere, William, 1853 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Beals, Royall, 1837 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Berry, George A., n.d. (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Boggs, Absalom, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Cassady, John, 1827 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Cauthorn, Ludy, 1834 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Croxton, Thomas, 1828 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Daly, Luke, 1834 (Box 34a, Folder 7)
      - Dennison, John, 1824 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Dunston, William, 1834 (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Discharge Papers - Foster-Newbold (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Foster, Jacob T., 1834 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Griffin, Joshua, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Hazlewood, William, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Horn, Jacob, 1825 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Jackson, John, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Leavandusky, Nicholas, 1828 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Martin, William, 1837 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Mayes, Ambrose, 1820 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - McLaughlin, Philip, 1834 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - McWilliams, John C., 1837 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Miller, George D., 1836 (Box 34, Folder 2)
      - Newbold, Charles, 1837 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Discharge Papers - Quigley-Wood (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Quigley, Dennis, 1828 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Richards, Richard, 1823 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Ritter, Edward M., 1823 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Roberts, Samuel, 1832 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Sandley, Griffin, 1821 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Simmons, Joel, 1829 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Sparrow, John, 1823 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Spillers, Ferdinand, 1838 (Box 34a, Folder 7)
      - Turner, Terry, 1831 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Vaughan, Lewis, 1833 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Whitings, Fabius, 1831 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Wood, Henry, 1853 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Wyckoff, Abraham, 1833 (Box 34a, Folder 7)
  - Rolls and Lists, 1775-1781, 1852-1857 and n.d., 0.11 cubic feet. (Box 34)
    - Key to 1812 printed payrolls and muster rolls, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - List of counties and regiments belonging to each, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - List of James Gray's pension payments, 1852 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - List of Revolutionary War battles, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Lists of officers and soldiers from miscellaneous wars, n.d. (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Muster rolls, 1813-1814, 8 leaves
    - Muster and descriptive rolls, 1847-1848 (Box 34a, Folder 8)
    - Payrolls from the Colonial Era, 1775? (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Return of Captain Carl Burnley, 16 May 1781 (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - "Rolls and Lists: Register of Officers of the War of 1812," (bound) n.d. (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - United States Cutter Service: List of officers, vessels and stations, 1857 (Box 34, Folder 12)
- Deeds and Plats, 1782-1881 and n.d., 0.23 cubic feet. (Boxes 34-35)
  Deeds and plats, 1782-1881 and n.d., pertaining to John K. Martin's land speculation and his service as a surveyor in the Richmond, Virginia, area. Includes deeds and plats for land in Richmond that Martin surveyed including the James River and its islands. Also contains correspondence concerning those deeds with city engineers.
  - Correspondence concerning deeds, 1850-1881 (Box 34, Folder 12a)
  - Deeds, 1836-1849 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - Deeds, 1850-1859 (Box 34, Folder 14)
  - Deeds, 1860-1878 (Box 34, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous oversize deeds and plats, 1872, 1874 and n.d. (Box 34a, Folder 9)
  - Plats of the James River and Its Islands, 1782-1851 (Box 35, Folder 1)
  - Plats of Richmond, 1872-1873 and n.d. (Box 35, Folder 2)
- Publications, ca. 1850-1871 and n.d., 0.23 cubic feet. (Box 35)
  Publications, ca. 1850-1871 and n.d., principally consisting of business cards, advertisement broadsides, and broadsides for events and political causes collected by John K. Martin. There are also blank forms, programs, and "An Epitaph on the Sheriffality."
  - "An Epitaph on the Sheriffality," n.d. (Box 35, Folder 3)
  - Blank forms, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 4)
  - Broadsides (advertisements), n.d. (Box 35, Folder 5)
  - Broadsides (advertisements - real estate), n.d. (Box 35, Folder 6)
  - Broadsides (events), n.d. (Box 35, Folder 7)
  - Broadsides (oversize), n.d. (Box 34a, Folder 10)
  - Broadsides (political), n.d. (Box 35, Folder 8)
  - Business cards, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - Business cards, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Business cards, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1852-1871 and n.d. (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Programs, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 13)
- Notes, ca. 1840-ca. 1882 and n.d., 0.68 cubic feet. (Box 35-36)
  Notes, ca. 1840-ca. 1882 and n.d., principally containing John K. Martin's research information that he compiled prior to disbursing land warrants for pension claimants. Includes abstracts and copies of court records including articles of agreement, deeds, plats, wills; land warrants; pension applications; genealogical notes and Bible records; military records. Several types of documents are often all recorded on the same page and the individual to whom the notes pertains has not been determined. As a result, the notes have been filed according to the manner in which Martin used them: as information relevant to disbursing land warrants. There are also notes concerning military records that were used to determine a claimant's qualification for pension. Filed at the end of the series are miscellaneous notes for which the research use could not be accurately deciphered or determined.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - Land warrants, 1871-1872 and n.d. (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Land warrants, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 15-20)
  - Land warrants, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
  - Liquor license applications, 1868-1870 (Box 36, Folder 6)
  - Military records, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 7-8)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 9-10)
- Envelopes, n.d., 2.25 cubic feet. (Box 37-41)
  These envelopes were separated from their respective correspondence at some point in the past.